Preliminary Guide to the Margaret McFadden Papers, 1961-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Margaret McFadden papers 1970-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McFadden, Margaret
57.2 linear feet Extent: 42,900 Items
Feminist scholar and activist; founder of the Women's Studies Program and professor in Interdisciplinary Studies at Appalachian State University in Boone, NC. Collection(42750 items, 57 lin. ft.; dated 1961-2009 and n.d.) comprises McFadden's professional papers. Includes published materials, conference files, materials related to the Southeastern Women's Studies Association (of which she is a founding member), correspondence, writings, teaching materials, and subject files. This collection also includes several additions; please consult the Collection Overview below to learn more about their contents. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
RL.00872
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Margaret McFadden Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift 2003-2013.
Biographical Note
Margaret McFadden is a feminist scholar and activist; founder of the Women's Studies Program and professor in Interdisciplinary Studies at Appalachian State University in Boone, NC.
Collection Overview
Collection (2003-0264) (14,000 items, 27 lin. ft.; dated [1970s]-2003 and n.d.) comprises McFadden's professional papers. Includes published materials, conference files, materials related to the Southeastern Women's Studies Association (of which she is a founding member), correspondence, writings, teaching materials, and subject files. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Addition (2005-0003) (2585 items, 5.0 lin. ft.; dated 1979-1999 and n.d.) comprises primarily research files, book notes, correspondence with other scholars and with her publisher, and drafts related to McFadden's book Golden Cables of Sympathy (1999). Also includes materials and notes from conferences she attended.
Addition (2005-0089) (2683 items, 4.2 lin. ft.; dated 1974-2005) comprises correspondence, subject files, reviews, research notes, and photographs related to Golden Cables of Sympathy; brochures, programs, and notes from conferences; academic files related to Ph.D students who were part of the Projects Demonstrating Excellence at the Union Institute Graduate School in Cincinnati, Ohio, 1995-2002.
Addition (2006-0001) (1125 items, 1.8 lin. ft.; dated 1989-1998) consists of correspondence, subject files, reviews, research notes, and academic files McFadden maintained during her professorship. There are also brochures, programs, and notes from conferences, including a paper delivered at the 8th Berkshire Conference on the History of Women, 8-10 June 1990. There are also newsletters; files McFadden kept while a Fulbright professor in Finland, 1991-1992; and ephemera.
Addition (2007-0124) (750 items; 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1982-1994) consists of correspondence, manuscripts, and research materials relating to women's studies books and articles by McFadden. Also included are grant proposals, recommendations, and book catalogs.
Addition (2007-0202) (2000 items; 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 1975-2007) includes research materials, notes, and academic files from McFadden's work as a professor.
Addition (2009-0192) (6500 items; 9.0 lin. ft.; dated 1970s-2009) includes materials from McFadden's courses and programs at Appalachian State's Interdisciplinary Studies program, including women's studies courses. Also includes materials from her Fulbrights to Finland and Austria, conference schedules, Southeastern Women's Studies Association (SEWSA) files, student evaluations, drafts of Golden Cables of Sympathy, and McFadden's historical women postcard collection.
Addition (2013-0164) (4500 items; 6.0 lin. ft; dated 1961-2009) includes research and academic files, including women's studies courses. Also includes materials from her Fulbright grants, SEWSA files, and professional engagements.
Subject Headings
McFadden, Margaret; Southeastern Women's Studies Association; Interdisciplinary approach in education; Women's studies; Postcards; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Related Material
This collection is closely related to the McFadden Family Papers, also contained in the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture. The McFadden Family Papers include personal correspondence, printed materials, photographs, diaries, and other ephemera centering around Margaret McFadden's parents, William and Glenora McFadden. Also included in the McFadden Family Papers are some of Margaret's classwork from her childhood and high school years, as well as correspondence from her to her parents in the 1970s.
Contents of Collection
- Margaret McFadden Papers (2003-0264), 1970s-2003, 44 Boxes
  Collection (2003-0264) (14,000 items, 27 lin. ft.; dated [1970s]-2003 and n.d.) comprises McFadden's professional papers. Includes published materials, conference files, materials related to the Southeastern Women's Studies Association (of which she is a founding member), correspondence, writings, teaching materials, and subject files. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
- Addition (2005-0003), 1979-1999 and no date, (9 Boxes)
  Addition (2005-0003) (2585 items, 5.0 lin. ft.; dated 1979-1999 and n.d.) comprises primarily research files, book notes, correspondence with other scholars and with her publisher, and drafts related to McFadden's book Golden Cables of Sympathy (1999). Also includes materials and notes from conferences she attended.
- Addition (2005-0089), 1974-2005, (7 Boxes)
  Addition (2005-0089) (2683 items, 4.2 lin. ft.; dated 1974-2005) comprises correspondence, subject files, reviews, research notes, and photographs related to Golden Cables of Sympathy; brochures, programs, and notes from conferences; academic files related to Ph.D students who were part of the Projects Demonstrating Excellence at the Union Institute Graduate School in Cincinnati, Ohio, 1995-2002.
- Addition (2006-0001), 1989-1998, (3 Boxes)
  Addition (2006-0001) (1125 items, 1.8 lin. ft.; dated 1989-1998) consists of correspondence, subject files, reviews, research notes, and academic files McFadden maintained during her professorship. There are also brochures, programs, and notes from conferences, including a paper delivered at the 8th Berkshire Conference on the History of Women, 8-10 June 1990. There are also newsletters; files McFadden kept while a Fulbright professor in Finland, 1991-1992; and ephemera.
- Addition (2007-0124), 1982-1994, (2 Boxes)
  Addition (2007-0124) (750 items; 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1982-1994) consists of correspondence, manuscripts, and research materials relating to women's studies books and articles by McFadden. Also included are grant proposals, recommendations, and book catalogs.
  - Drafts of articles and research notes (Box 1)
    - Boston Teenagers Debate the Woman Question, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Thinking Woman (Box 1)
  - Grants and fellowships (Box 1)
    - NEH grant, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1986 (Box 1)
    - Other grant files (Box 1)
  - Recommendation for Dana Greene (Box 1)
  - Syllabus - Women and Fiction (Box 1)
  - Papers related to All Over the Map (Box 2)
  - Drafts of articles by other authors (Box 2)
  - NORA manuscripts (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of Dr. Elizabeth Bartlett (Box 2)
- Addition (2007-0202), 1975-2007, (5 Boxes) (Box 2)
  Addition (2007-0202) (2000 items; 3.0 lin. ft.; dated 1975-2007) includes research materials, notes, and academic files from McFadden's work as a professor.
  - Course materials (Box 1)
    - Films from Fiction (Box 1)
    - Women and Film (Box 1)
  - Course materials, 1980s (Box 2)
    - Women and Film (Box 2)
      - Planning (Box 2)
      - Evaluations (Box 2)
      - Student papers (Box 2)
      - Film lists (Box 2)
  - Course materials, 1970s (Box 3)
  - Conference materials, 2000s (Box 3)
  - Course materials, 1970s-2005 (Box 4)
    - Interdisciplinary Studies (Box 4)
    - Women's Studies (Box 4)
  - Course materials (Box 5)
- Addition (2009-0192), 1970s-2009, (6 boxes) (Box 5)
  Addition (2009-0192) (6500 items; 9.0 lin. ft.; dated 1970s-2009) includes materials from McFadden's courses and programs at Appalachian State's Interdisciplinary Studies program, including women's studies courses. Also includes materials from her Fulbrights to Finland and Austria, conference schedules, Southeastern Women's Studies Association (SEWSA) files, student evaluations, drafts of Golden Cables of Sympathy, and McFadden's historical women postcard collection.
  - Newspapers about the ASU women's studies department, March 2009 (Box 1)
  - SEWSA travel grants, 2007 (Box 1)
  - NWSAJ budget, 2003 (Box 1)
  - NWSA Journal national board meeting, January 2007 (Box 1)
  - NWSA Journal annual report notes, 1999 (Box 1)
  - SEWSA, 2005 (Box 1)
  - SEWSA proposals, 2009 (Box 1)
  - Fulbright reference, 2005 (Box 1)
  - May trip to Finland and Hungary, 2006 (Box 1)
  - 100 Scholars research award, 2006 (Box 1)
  - ASU miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Duke colloquium, August 2005 (Box 1)
  - Feminist Time/Nation Time, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Sally Wagner and Matilda Gage, 2008 (Box 1)
  - IFRWH, 2005 (Box 1)
  - NWSA Feminist pedagogy (Box 1)
  - Steinem lunch, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Women's Center brown bag, November 2007 (Box 1)
  - International Lawrence Durrell Society, 2007 (Box 1)
  - UNC Asheville, March 2007 (Box 1)
  - Duke Symposium, October 2007 (Box 1)
  - Nordic Advisory Committee Meeting, October 2005 (Box 1)
  - Jeannette Stokes, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Graduate Faculty Status application, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Fairfield, Illinois, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Xerox for NY (Box 1)
  - URC Grant-Schwimmer, etc., 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  - Dr. Nickless, UNC Asheville lecture, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Claudia Koonz, 2005 (Box 1)
  - SEWSA-Valdosta/Schwimmer, 2006 (Box 1)
  - American Historical Review-Blackwell review, 2005 (Box 1)
  - CLGH Prize, 2004-2005 (Box 1)
  - PTR miscellaneous articles and drafts, news, ASU Women's Studies department, 2005-2007 (Box 1)
  - 100 Scholars appointment, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Dr. C.A. Cranston, March 2006 (Box 1)
  - Sheela-na-gig, March 2006 (Box 1)
  - Austria Fulbright talk and panel, 2005-2006 (Box 1)
  - Yale blog conference, October 2005 (Box 1)
  - Bingham Center Symposium, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Gender, War, and Nation in 20th Century Europe, UNC, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Post-tenure review, Spring 2005 (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - World Congress on Matriarchal Studies, 2005 (Box 1)
  - ASU correspondence, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Women's Studies Symposium, Perdue, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Matilda Joslyn Gage Foundation (Box 1)
  - Herstory! ASU Women's Leadership Conference, March 2008 (Box 1)
  - Duke Gender and Ethnic Conflict Symposium, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Women's Studies brochures (Box 1)
  - Berkshire Conference, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Salem Press, Masterplots/Christian Literature, 2006 (Box 2)
  - ASU Humanities Series, 2006-2007 (Box 2)
  - Loose pages re: Women's Studies (Box 2)
  - Women's Caucus, ASU, 1970s (Box 2)
  - Feminist Theory workshop, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Feminist Theory classication paper, 1980s (Box 2)
  - ILA/Emory, 2003 (Box 2)
  - Women as a Minority Group (Box 2)
  - Androgyny, SEWSA conference, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Jokes and notes (Box 2)
  - Doris Lessing, 1970s (Box 2)
  - Articles, 1970s (Box 2)
  - Naturewriting, 1970s (Box 2)
  - Supplemental materials, including ASU course syllabi and readings, 1970s (Box 2)
  - Student Course Evaluations, 1970s-1990s (32 envelopes) (Box 2)
  - Watauga College, April 1978 (Box 2)
  - Watauga team teaching workshop, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Herstory evaluations (Box 2)
  - Ph.D. diploma from Emory (Box 3)
  - Factory Second Food and Tevre Madre art (Box 3)
  - Food films course, 2003 (Box 3)
  - On my door and correspondence, 2003 (Box 3)
  - Austrian correspondence and clippings, 2004 (Box 3)
  - NWSAJ and speaker flyers (Box 3)
  - Reel Food paper, revisions and final, April 2003 (Box 3)
  - Torino, Slow Food, Hidden Kitchens, etc. (Box 3)
  - Food films for Reel Food (Box 3)
  - Taxco, Mexico trip, October 2000 (Box 3)
  - SLOW Food, including Sicily (Box 3)
  - Not for Ourselves Alone review, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Boston Teenagers manuscript, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Stanton/Anthony film by Ken Burns, 1999 (Box 3)
  - NC Women's History Symposium, 1990 (Box 3)
  - The American Woman: Herstory off-campus presentations, 1984 (Box 3)
  - G. Lerner: American Women, 1870-Present and Feminist Theory (Box 3)
  - Women and the Law course, Fall 1986 (Box 3)
  - Black Women's Voices: Autobiography, UCCS, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Wollstonecraft (Box 3)
  - Madrid panel, July 2008 (Box 3)
  - Qualitative Research folder (Box 3)
  - Grand Canyon, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Color Purple review by Margaret McFadden (Box 3)
  - Pictures and posters, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Brown Girl Brownstones crossword puzzle (Box 3)
  - Women's Studies-early, 1985-1995 (Box 3)
  - Personal letters and cards, early 1980s-1990s (Box 3)
  - Angelou's All God's Children Need Traveling Shoes reviews and notes (Box 3)
  - Women's Studies course materials (Box 3)
  - Margaret of Denmark, Norway, and Sweden (Box 3)
  - Iceland women (Box 3)
  - No Man's Land, sexchanges, vol. 21, review (Box 3)
  - UNC Press: Women in Medieval Scandinavia (Box 3)
  - H. Taylor Mill biography (Box 3)
  - Rape in Bosnia, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Eastern Europe scholars, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous loose papers (Box 4)
  - Pictures, etc. (Box 4)
  - Anna Wheeler paper for Hypatia, 1989 (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Gradebook (Box 4)
  - Louis and Clark College Gender Studies Symposium, 2008 (Box 4)
  - Fulbright orientation, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Notes and writings (Box 4)
  - ASU graduate teaching, 1980s (Box 4)
  - NY Loft application, 1986 (Box 4)
  - Harriet Silius's Festskrift, January 2008 (Box 4)
  - SEWSA, Writing Women's Lives panel, 2008 (Box 4)
  - ASU Humanities programs, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Women's Studies Symposium, Perdue, November 2007 (Box 4)
  - General Honors Director application, 1989 (Box 4)
  - 19th century women's preachers, March 2006 (Box 4)
  - Fairfield boarders, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Protest letter, April 2006 (Box 4)
  - Oxford Encyclopedia of Women in World History, 2007-2008 (Box 4)
  - IFRWH Bulgaria, August 2007 (Box 4)
  - SEWSA roundtable paper, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Union Graduate School, Theresa Burris (Box 4)
  - Fulbright in Austria materials, 2002-2003 (Box 4)
  - Course evaluations, 1996-1999 (Box 4)
  - UNC EP October 2007 (Box 4)
  - NWSA-NWSAJ mess, Spring 2009 (Box 4)
  - Ida Blam paper, women's history (Box 4)
  - Kath K's poetry (Box 4)
  - Unequal sisters Finland lectures (Box 4)
  - Klagenfurt correspondence, 2004 (Box 4)
  - FJN, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Curriculum vitae, 2004 (Box 4)
  - Overview lecture on Feminist Classics (Box 4)
  - From Voting Rights to Social Revolution lecture (Box 4)
  - Alpha Chi speech, April 2003 (Box 4)
  - Women Artists of Western NC, 2006 (Box 5)
  - Continuities and Discontinuities: Women's Movement International Conference, 2004 (Box 5)
  - UNC Adventures in Ideas, 2007 (Box 5)
  - International Federation for Research in Women's History, August 2007 (Box 5)
  - Women's Studies conferences and programs, 1990s-2000s (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - NWSA materials, 1990s-2000s (Box 5)
  - SSHRC Canada grant, 2005 (Box 5)
  - Notes for introduction of Gloria Steinem, 2008 (Box 5)
  - Women's Worlds (Korea) conference, 2005 (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Women's Studies to sort and do miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Interdisciplinary Studies colloquium, 1960s (Box 5)
  - Recommendations, 1998s (Box 5)
  - Whitney Foundation, 1981 (Box 5)
  - Shadow Narrative, SEWHA, October 2006 (Box 5)
  - ASU (Arizona) application, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Arizona State and San Francisco State application, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Graduate Faculty (Box 5)
  - Fulbright in Finland, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Loose pages of women's studies materials (Box 5)
  - Golden Cables of Sympathy, master and editorial drafts (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Sherman Paul's Nature Writing invitation, 1989 (Box 6)
  - ASU Interdisciplinary Studies reports, 1980s (Box 6)
    Includes reports to the chancellor, with course syllabi, self-evaluations, questionnaires, newsletters, all relating to Women's Studies and Interdisciplinary Studies.
  - Postcard collection (Box 6)
- Addition (2013-0164), 1961-2009, (4 boxes) (Box 6)
  - Coursework and research files; materials from Fulbright grants, SEWSA files, research, and professional engagements (Box 1)
  - Research files on nineteenth-century United States and Europe with an emphasis on women travelers (Box 2)
  - Book proofs, drafts and other personal papers (Box 3)
  - Personal papers, professional correspondence (Box 4)